Inventory of the Charles Brown Papers, 1792-1888.
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, College of William and Mary
Charles Brown Papers, 1792-1888.
Special Collections, College of William and Mary
Mss. 39.1 B84
896 items
Letters, accounts and legal papers of Dr. Charles Brown.
Charles Brown
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
Purchased ca. 1938
Biographical/Historical Information
Charles Brown was a physician who resided in Charlottesville, Virginia in the early nineteenth century and who served as sheriff of Albemarle County, Virginia.
Scope and Content Information
Letters, accounts and legal papers of Dr. Charles Brown. Collection includes letters, 1813-1818, concerning patients (including slaves). Includes land signed by Henry Lee and John Tyler, items relating to "Actonplace" [Acton] English estate of William Jennings and plats of land in Albemarle County, Virginia; as well as letters of members of the Brown family.
Arrangement
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged chronologically by date with those items without dates located at the end.
Organization
These papers have been organized into four series and two sub-series: 1. Letters,1813-1877 (Folders 1-4); 2. Accounts and Papers of Charles Brown, 1810-1877 (Folders 5-8); 3. Papers relating to Other Members of the Brown family, 1751-1888 (Folder 9); 4. Papers belonging to other persons, 1796-1850(Folder 9).
INDEX TERMS
Family Names:
Brown family.
Persons:
Jennings, William, d. 1798.; Lee, Henry, 1756-1818.; Tyler, John, 1790-1862.
Subjects:
Medicine--Virginia--History--19th century.; Slavery--Virginia--History--19th century.; Slavery--Southern States--History--19th century.; Real property--Virginia.; Sheriffs--Virginia--History--19th century.
Geographical Names:
Acton (Eng.: Estate); Albemarle County (Va.)--History--19th century.
COMPONENT LIST AND DESCRIPTIONS
  Series 1: Letters
- Letters, 1813-1877. (Folder 1-4)
  Letters that were sent to or written by Charles Brown.
  - letters relating to the estate of William Jennings of Actonplace England, 1850-1877. (Folder 1)
  - Letters from or concerning patients, 1813-1818., 193 items. (Folder 1-3)
    - John Allphin., 4 items. (Folder 1)
    - Mary Ballard., 1 item. (Folder 1)
    - W[?] Ballard., 1 item. (Folder 1)
    - Henry Barnett., 1 item. (Folder 1)
    - Richard M. Beckett., 1 item. (Folder 1)
    - J. Bishop., 1 item. (Folder 1)
    - John Brockman., 2 items. (Folder 1)
    - B. Brown., 1 item. (Folder 1)
    - Beanis[?] Brown., 1 item. (Folder 1)
    - Bernard Brown., 9 items. (Folder 1)
    - Bezaleel Brown., 19 items. (Folder 1)
      5 letters concern slaves.
    - Brightbery Brown., 2 items. (Folder 1)
      1 letter concerns a slave.
    - Elijah Brown., 1 item. (Folder 1)
    - T. H. Brown., 4 items. (Folder 1)
    - William Brown., 1 item. (Folder 1)
    - Charles Burris., 2 items. (Folder 1)
    - John H. Carr., 1 item. (Folder 1)
    - Willis Carr., 1 item. (Folder 1)
    - Law[rence?] T. Catlett., 1 item. (Folder 1)
    - Hugh Chisholm., 1 item. (Folder 1)
    - Thomas K. Clarke., 2 items. (Folder 1)
      Both letters concern slaves.
    - William Coleman's wife., 1 item. (Folder 1)
      Note: On the bottom of the sheet appears a note in the same hand signed James Keaton.
    - Mrs. Coles., 1 item. (Folder 1)
      Letter concerns a slave.
    - Georges Crank., 2 items. (Folder 1)
    - Augustus Darrell., 1 item. (Folder 2)
    - Edmund Davis., 6 items. (Folder 2)
      2 letters concern slaves.
    - Ruben Davis., 1 item. (Folder 2)
    - Robert Davis., 2 items. (Folder 2)
    - James Douglass., 1 item. (Folder 2)
    - William J. Douglass[?]., 1 item. (Folder 2)
    - Brice Edwards., 1 item. (Folder 2)
    - Dabney Ellis., 1 item. (Folder 2)
    - Jemima Fretwell., 1 item. (Folder 2)
    - David Fowler., 1 item. (Folder 2)
    - Richard Gaines., 3 items. (Folder 2)
    - John Gardner., 1 item. (Folder 2)
    - Elijah Garrison., 1 item. (Folder 2)
    - Sally Garrison., 1 item. (Folder 2)
    - Garland Garth., 11 items. (Folder 2)
      4 letters concern slaves.
    - Jessee Garth., 2 items. (Folder 2)
    - Thomas Garth., 2 items. (Folder 2)
    - William Garth., 1 item. (Folder 2)
    - John Gillum., 1 item. (Folder 2)
    - John Grinstead., 1 item. (Folder 2)
    - Benjamin Hardin., 6 items. (Folder 2)
    - C. Harris., 1 item. (Folder 2)
    - John Harris., 5 items. (Folder 2)
    - Mary Harris., 1 item. (Folder 2)
    - N. Harris., 1 item. (Folder 2)
    - James Horsley., 1 item. (Folder 2)
    - [?] Howard., 1 item. (Folder 2)
    - Thomas Irvin., 1 item. (Folder 2)
    - P. C. Jarman., 2 items. (Folder 2)
    - Michael Johnson., 1 item. (Folder 2)
    - James Keaton., 1 item. (Folder 2)
    - David I. Lewis., 2 items. (Folder 3)
    - Jesse Lewis., 3 items. (Folder 3)
    - Darky McCord., 1 item. (Folder 3)
    - Robert McCullock, Jr., 2 items. (Folder 3)
    - Reuben Mansfield., 5 items. (Folder 3)
    - Thomas Marr., 1 item. (Folder 3)
    - Jennings Maupin., 1 item. (Folder 3)
    - John Maupin., 1 item. (Folder 3)
    - James Michie., 1 item. (Folder 3)
    - John A. Michie., 1 item. (Folder 3)
    - William Michie., 3 items. (Folder 3)
    - Wilson Mills., 1 item. (Folder 3)
    - Martha R. Moore., 1 item. (Folder 3)
    - Noble Moore., 2 items. (Folder 3)
    - James Old., 1 item (Folder 3)
    - George Perry., 2 items. (Folder 3)
    - J. C. Ragland., 1 item. (Folder 3)
    - John Robinson., 4 items. (Folder 3)
    - John Rodes., 2 items. (Folder 3)
    - P. [?] Rogers., 1 item. (Folder 3)
    - William Rodgers., 1 item. (Folder 3)
    - Thomas L. Shelton., 1 item. (Folder 3)
    - Spencer Simmons., 1 item. (Folder 3)
    - John Smith., 2 items. (Folder 3)
    - Samuel Smithson., 1 item. (Folder 3)
    - William Sullivan., 1 item. (Folder 3)
    - Joel Terrell., 2 items. (Folder 3)
    - E. I. Thompson., 1 item. (Folder 3)
    - Lucy Thompson., 3 items. (Folder 3)
    - Nathaniel Thompson., 2 items. (Folder 3)
    - William [?] Tomlin., 1 item. (Folder 3)
    - Minoah Via., 1 item. (Folder 3)
    - John Watson., 1 item. (Folder 3)
    - Geoge Wayt., 2 items. (Folder 3)
    - William C. Webb., 1 item. (Folder 3)
    - T. Wells., 1 item. (Folder 3)
    - Abraham Wiant., 1 item. (Folder 3)
    - John A. Wilson., 1 item. (Folder 3)
    - Micajah Woods., 2 items. (Folder 3)
    - J.G. Wright., 2 items. (Folder 3)
    - Jeremiah[?] Yancey., 1 item. (Folder 3)
    - Unidentified., 2 items. (Folder 3)
  - Letters, 1805-1851., 23 items. (Folder 4)
    Includes 2 letters to Dr. Ragland.
  Series 2: Accounts and Papers of Charles Brown
- Accounts and Papers of Charles Brown, 1810-1877. (Folder 5-8)
  Important accounts and papers that were kept and used by Charles Brown
  - Accounts of Charles Brown, 1810-1877., 396 items. (Folder 5-7)
  - Will, n.d., 1 item. (Folder 8)
  - Deed, 1821., 1 item. (Folder 8)
    A deed given by William D. Taylor, United States tax collector for the 18th district of Virginia, to Charles Brown, covering a tract of land in Albemarle County, Virginia.
  - Land warrant, 1822., 1 item. (Folder 8)
    A warrant issued by John Taylor, Governor of Virginia, granting a tract of land in Albemarle County, Virginia, to Charles Brown.
  - Land papers, 1814-1825., 3 items. (Folder 8)
    Papers concerning other lands owned by Charles Brown.
  - Medical Licenses, 1814-1815, 1815-1816., 2 items. (Folder 8)
    Licenses to practice medicine.
  - Bonds, 1841-1843., 10 items. (Folder 8)
    Bonds given by persons appointed by Charles Brown, sheriff of Albemarle County, Virginia, to act as deputies.
  - Suits, 1842-1843., 7 items. (Folder 8)
    Suits against Charles Brown, sheriff of Albemarle County, Virginia.
  - Suit, 1876., 1 item. (Folder 8)
    Suit of G. T. Owens against Charles Brown.
  - Judgement, n.d., 1 item. (Folder 8)
    Judgement against Charles Brown.
  - Horse ownership papers, 1841., 3 items. (Folder 8)
    Papers concerning the joint ownership of a horse by Charles Brown and John Fagg.
  - An article, 1851., 1 item. (Folder 8)
    An article on the habits and economy of the honey bee, by Charles Brown.
  - Patent papers, 1853-1869., 10 items. (Folder 8)
    Papers relating to a patent for a process of preserving wood discovered by Charles Brown.
  - Prescriptions, n.d., 4 items. (Folder 8)
  - Verse, n.d., 1 item. (Folder 8)
  - Estate settlement, 1880., 1 item. (Folder 8)
    Power of attorney given to A. R. Brown and Elvira S. Ayres in the settlement of the Charles Brown estate.
  Series 3: Papers relating to other members of the Brown Family
- Papers relating to other members of the Brown family, 1751-1888. (Folder 9)
  Included are letters, accounts, boundary and land identifications, and estate settlement papers.
  - Letters, 1876., 3 items. (Folder 9)
  - Accounts, 1816-1888., 51 items. (Folder 9)
    Papers consisting of invoices, receipts, etc. from members of the Brown family
    - Miss Brown, 1835-1844., 2 items. (Folder 9)
    - Mr. Brown, 1816-1849., 8 items. (Folder 9)
    - Mrs. Brown, n.d., 1 item. (Folder 9)
    - Mrs. Doctor Brown, 1821., 1 item. (Folder 9)
    - Asa B. Brown, 1821-1822., 2 items. (Folder 9)
    - B. Brown, 1845., 2 items. (Folder 9)
    - B. O. & C. Brown, 1842-1843., 20 items. (Folder 9)
    - Bernard M. Brown's estate, 1807-1829., 6 items. (Folder 9)
    - Bezaleel J. Brown, 1845-1888., 5 items. (Folder 9)
    - C.H. Brown, 1841., 1 item. (Folder 9)
    - Ira B. Brown, 1834., 1 item. (Folder 9)
    - William H. Brown, 1843-1844., 2 items. (Folder 9)
  - Boundary papers, 1751-1756., 6 items. Copies. (Folder 9)
    Papers giving boundaries of land owned by Benjamin and Bezaleel Brown.
  - Boundary papers, 1792., 1 item. (Folder 9)
    A warrant signed by Henry Lee, governor of Virginia, granting to Bazeleel [Bezaleel] Brown a tract of land in Albemarle County, Virginia.
  - Estate papers, 1870-1877., 8 items. (Folder 9)
    Papers relating to the settlement of the estate of Judith Brown.
  Series 4: Papers belonging to other persons
- Papers belong to other persons, 1796-1850., 76 items. (Folder 9)
  Papers that were created for or by persons other than the Brown family and found among Charles Brown's papers.
  - Land Warrant, 1796., 1 item. Copy. (Folder 9)
    A warrant granting to John Barkley a tract of land in Albemarle County, Virginia.
  - Other legal papers, 1823-1845., 10 items. (Folder 9)
  - Accounts of Jonathon Gions, 1843-1845., 7 items. (Folder 9)
  - Accounts of Valentine Head, 1842., 11 items. (Folder 9)
  - Other Accounts, 1813-1850., 47 items. (Folder 9)